<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A litel treatise ageynste the mutterynge of some papistis in corners</title>
            <author>Swinnerton, Thomas, d. 1554.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16009</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840013</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176371</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240923242</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 23551.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S104274</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840013e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16009)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176371)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 122:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A litel treatise ageynste the mutterynge of some papistis in corners</title>
                  <author>Swinnerton, Thomas, d. 1554.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Tho. Bertheleti,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. M.D.XXXIIII. [1534]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Swinnerton by John Bale.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C² .</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19177 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176371:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176371:1"/>
            <p> ❧ A LITEL TREATISE <hi>ageynste the mutterynge of some papistis in corners.</hi> ❧</p>
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS</p>
            <p>THO. BERTHELETI.</p>
            <p>AN. M. D. XXXIIII.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:176371:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:176371:2"/>
            <head>TREATISE</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or so moche that somme controuersie, at the fyrste sight of certayne bokes, of late put forthe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the bysshoppe of Rome, called the pope, rose amonge the people, some meruaylynge, that we shulde so sodeynely relynquysshe and forsake that custome, that had so longe continued, and some were so blynded, that they thought it shulde be ageynste our feythe, to forsake the pope (but I thynke they, that so sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, dyd put more their trust in the pope, then in Christe.) And the moste parte of that sorte made none other reason but this: That if we do well nowe, thus to forsake the pope, then all our forefathers dyd amisse, and so dyd we also, tylle this presente tyme, which were vnder obedience and sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection of the byshoppe of Rome, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med pope: and they beleued, that he had auctoritie and power to make la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes,
<pb facs="tcp:176371:3"/> &amp; to bynde &amp; leuse what, &amp; whom he wold. This was the greattest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that many men made: whiche I suppose they dyd eyther of affection, orels throughe ignoraunce. I haue thought it therfore very expedient to labour for my power, to answere and partlye to satisfie their doubtes, to the intent that after they knowe the truthe, they shulde be ashamed so to clatter in corners ageinst it, and also (all thynges knowne) against theyr owne profite. And shortly to answere vnto theyr fore made reason, I saye that if our forefathers dyd beleue the pope to haue had suche a power and auctorytie gyuen hym by god, that he myght make lawes, and order all mattiers and businessis of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, after his owne luste &amp; pleasure (like as verye many of theym haue done this. viii. C. yeres and more) then were they blynd and in a wrong beleue, whiche thynge I thynke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
<pb facs="tcp:176371:3"/> they dyd not, but that al our fore fathers, as many as were lerned and wyse, knewe it for certeyne, that all suche auctorytie and power, as the pope had, more then al other byshops or ouer and vppon the same, was not immediately gyuen hym by god, but he had it granted him by kynges and princis, and the consente of men, or els came by it by wronge vsurpation and tirrannye. For the same fathers knewe righte well, that by the lawes of god, all bysshoppes were, and yet nowe be in power and auctoritie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, and that the byshop of Rome in al poyntes of our fayth, and belefe is subiecte vnto holye scripture and the generall counsell, and may by the auctoritie of the same as wel be depo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed for sufficient causes, as any other byshoppe may: And this right welle maye they knowe that rede suche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers, as bothe for lyfe and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge haue ben euer moste approued
<pb facs="tcp:176371:4"/> in Christis church, as saynt Ciprian, saint Hierom, saint Ambrose, seint Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gustine, with other lyke. The whiche thyng surely coulde neuer haue bene tru, yf that the pope (as som papistes both write &amp; sai) be heed of the church &amp; may do in erth what he wyl, &amp; al be it that many good simple &amp; vnlerned folke haue thought the gret vsurped power of the bishop of Rome, to haue ben giuen to hym by the lawe of god, (hervnto induced by such as sekinge their owne profyt, in the mayntenāce therof, haue ben accoūted lerned) yet was not this mater vnto them dāna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nor they therfore so moch to be bla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, but rather suche as haue sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them herin. But this not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge, to sey truely in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is not so moche to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what our fore faders haue done, as what they oughte to do. For as their good exāples must be folowed, so theyr yuel muste be fled. Almighty <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 20.</note> god, by the mouthe of his prophette
<pb facs="tcp:176371:4"/> Ezechiel, saythe: Walke not in your fathers rules, neither kepe their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemētis, ne be not poluted with their idols: for I am youre lorde god, but walke ye in my cōmandemētis (seyth he) and kepe my iudgemētis, and ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyl <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> them. &amp;c. Also sainct Paule, one of our best fore fathers, biddith vs fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe him, euyn as he folowid Christ. Marke nowe. He saythe, euyn as he folowed Christe: meanynge, that in no case we shulde folowe hym, where as he swarued from Christe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any of our fore fathers, of igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance, or for their owne glorie or lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, haue brought any custome in to Christis churche, contrarie to truthe and his holy doctrine: we oughte of duetie (refusinge suche erroneous cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stome) to folowe the truthe. For if sainct Paule hym selfe (whiche with a feruent zele kepte his fathers tradi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions and lawes, ye and fiersely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutid the transgressors of the same) had walked styll in his fathers step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,
<pb facs="tcp:176371:5"/> and hadde not forsaken them to come to the truthe: he had neuer ben saued. Herunto accordeth sayncte Augustins wordis, in his secōd boke intitled <hi>De unico baptismo,</hi> Truthe ones knowen (saith he) custome must giue place to the truthe. For who douteth that custome ought to gyue place to the truthe ones publyshed? Nor let no man preferre Custome afore reson and truthe: for alweys Reason and truthe putteth custome out of place.</p>
            <p>To this sayenge of saint Augustine <note place="margin">
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>si cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>suetud. di.</hi> 8.</note> agreith saint Gregori, writing thus: If percase thou leyest ageynst vs cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, it muste be regarded, that our <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 8.</note> lorde seyth: I am the wey, I am the truthe, I am the lyfe. He sayde not, that I am olde vsage and Custome, but the Truthe. And certaynely (as sainct Cyprian sayth) euery custome, be it neuer so olde, neuer so cōmon &amp; general, is to be vtterly forsaken for the truthe sake: and that vsage, that
<pb facs="tcp:176371:5"/> is contrarie to the truthe, is vtterly to be destroyed. Wherfore not with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standinge any vsage or custome, it is laufull, and standeth very well with goddis worde, the truthe ones kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, to withdrawe our obedience frō the byshop of Rome: by ouer moche obedience vnto whom of longe seson we haue ben seducid and ledde out of the right wey, and haue alowed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his vices for high vertues.</p>
            <p>Herof saincte Gregorie warneth vs <note place="margin">2. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>c. Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi.</hi>
               </note> to take heede, sayenge: Subiectes ought to be admonished, not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto their prelatis more thā is expediente, lest whiles they ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoir them selfes to be obediēt to men more than nede is, they shulde be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to reuerence, alowe, &amp; preyse theyr vices.</p>
            <p>Se here, saint Gregori aloweth not suche obedience, wherby prelatis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces shulde be meynteyned. And sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in suche thinges, wherin they opē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:176371:6"/> sclaunder the churche, it standeth right wel with the lawe of god, open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to reproue them: and from this the bishop of Rome, all though he were ten tymes called Pope, is not except: orlels we muste nedes graunte, that saint Paule did amisse, whiche repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued Peter (that is callid the prince of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.</note> the apostols) euen in the face, that is to sey, before the holle congregacion of the churche. If saynt Paule dyd thus to saint Peter, that was institu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by Christe hym selfe, and whanne saincte Peter erred not in his feythe, but for eatinge of meatis prohibite to the iewes, whiche was but a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and at that tyme hauynge no strengthe: howe moche more thanne ought the pope to be reproued of all good christen people, the whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge chosen and institutid by men, wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thout myracle or reuelacion (I wyll not sey ofte tymes by symonie) dothe not only fle from the folowing of our
<pb facs="tcp:176371:6"/> sauiour Iesu Christe, and his blessed apostoll Peter, whose successour the pope and papistis seye that he is, but also he excludeth clene Christe with his mekenes, pouertie, and obediēce, expressed in the holy euāgelistis, and for Christe he wolbe knowen, and for Christis lawes, he bryngethe forthe lawes and traditions of his owne di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uisyng, the whiche wollen hym to be lorde and syre ouer all, to be stronge, riche, and myghty, and that all men shulde be obedient to his wyll.</p>
            <p>And all thoughe some bringe in, in this place here, this texte, <hi>Credo san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Ecclesiam catholicam,</hi> it can litel help their argument. For I suppose, that there was neuer wise man so farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer seen, neither of our forefathers, nor of those that be in our tyme, that beleued, that the Pope is the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke holy Churche: but they knewe well, that he is but a membre therof, and the childe of our mother the holy
<pb facs="tcp:176371:7"/> churche (if he be a true christen man) and brother to euery christen man.</p>
            <p>And for a playne proffe that this is true, our sauiour Iesu Christ taught vs al to praye one prayour: Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>matt.</hi> 6.</note> that arte in heuen. &amp;c. Then se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that we all haue but one father, whiche is in heuen, and one mother the holy churche in erthe, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feste and clere to all the worlde, that the pope and we be al bretherne (if he be a true christen man.) And then se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the Pope is oure brother, why shulde not he haue &amp; abyde brotherly correction, accordinge to the lawe of the gospell, where Christe saythe: If <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>Luc.</hi> 17.</note> thy brother offende the, correcte hym betwene the and hym alone.</p>
            <p>And if some wyl yet sey (supposinge that he hath suche auctoritie of god, as he presumeth to haue) that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pope ought not to be thus layde vnto, and so sharply constrained to shewe to the worlde, what auctorite he hath to do,
<pb facs="tcp:176371:7"/> as he longe hath done, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to dispēce in any case ageynst the lawe of god: then the apostols and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 11.</note> brethern ought not in Iudea to haue layde it to saint Peters charge, when he was come to Hierusalem, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>strayne hym to shewe the reason why he viseted and taught Cornelius the gentile, with whome by the iewes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes he ought not to haue cōpanied.</p>
            <p>And therfore let no man thynke, but that our forefathers toke the pope al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weye to be a man, a synner, &amp; suche a one as might well erre, &amp; suche a one as ought moche rather to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his lyfe and state, then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apostel Peter for viseting of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius: yea &amp; our fore fathers neuer toke hym for any other but suche one as might wel and ought to be refour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, corrected, ye and clene deposed and put downe, as many popis haue ben in tymes paste, by kyngis &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, wherof no man is ignorant, that
<pb facs="tcp:176371:8"/> hath redde the stories that intreate of the businesse of Christendome. And therfore no man ought to marueile &amp; mutturre in corners, as thoughe we shulde nowe attempt a thinge in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glande, whiche our fore fathers had neuer attempted in tymes paste.</p>
            <p>For vndoubtedly all men, that were before tyme, whiche were wise &amp; well lerned, and that knewe Christe &amp; his doctrine, and that willed Christe and his doctrine to reigne, &amp; to be knowē &amp; folowid of al christen people, did ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horre the pompose and worldly state of the pope, and his tradicions, that he made to vpholde the same: &amp; they sparid not to speke and write ageynst his abhominable abusions: and for that cause they were alwey put either to silence orels to dethe, by the great princis of the worlde, at the instance of the pope &amp; his papistis, of whome there is spronge vp to great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre in euery region and coūtrey: and
<pb facs="tcp:176371:8"/> al that was by reason that the noble princis them selfe were vnlernid, and coude not iuge in suche matters, but they gaue alwey credēce to the falce, subtyle, and slye persuasions of the pope and his bolsterers. But nowe thankes be to almyghtie god, frome whom cometh al goodnes, the father <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 1.</note> of lightis, the princis hartis beginne to be lyghted with the knowledge of Christis doctrine, and they begynne to perceyue, what wey this wily wat hath walked all this lōge while: and what great hurte, wronge, &amp; oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion they haue sufferedde: And howe moche more iniury he entended to do to our mooste gratious soueraygne lorde the kinge, whose highnes, with his moste honorable counsaile, haue bene constrayned, by theyr great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and study, to trie out the truthe. For if they them selfe hadde not, by theyr diligente studie, sought out his false fraude, the popishe forme shuld
<pb facs="tcp:176371:9"/> neuer haue ben refourmedde, nor it shulde neuer haue ben knowne, that the pope is but a byshop in his owne diocese, and that he ought to preache and teche the people, &amp; that he ought not to occupie lordeshyppes of this worlde, but vtterly to refuse al world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly honoure, delite, or pleasure, in ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and renome, as Christe and his blessed apostols did, whom he ought to folowe.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> farthermore to sey, that the kingis highnes is displeasid, bicause the Pope wyll not folowe his gracis mynde in his moste weyghtye cause: is a sayenge bothe false and vntrue, and it besemeth no louynge subiecte so to surmise. For the verie truthe is, that his grace hath of longe season vtterly refused the popis iudgement in his great and waighty cause, and not nowe sodaynely, as these men i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin: and hath cōmitted the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge therof vnto all the beste lerned
<pb facs="tcp:176371:9"/> vniuersities, and to all the beste ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in christendome, as vnto su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that for theyr lerninge coude best iudge in goddis lawe, wheron his gracis cause holly hangeth, neuer in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendynge to stande to the popis iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, onlesse he iudged the same, that the lawe of god wolde hym her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to do, and that not bycause of his power and auctorite, but for the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes sake. To the whiche lerned men and vniuersities determination (as a prince moste iuste and vertuous) he alwey offered hym selfe to stande and abyde, and accordynge therto hath nowe prosecuted his cause. whiche thinge ye maye well witte his grace wolde neuer haue doone, excepte he hadde seen the lawe of god clerely on his side: Nor so many vniuersities &amp; excellente lerned men, wolde neuer haue so determined, excepte it hadde stande styffely with the lawe of god.</p>
            <p>If his gracis matter had not ben, as
<pb facs="tcp:176371:10"/> afore is sayde: it had ben farre more easye for his highnes, if he had reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nid the popis auctorite sufficient ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, to haue shortly corrupted hym, beinge but one man, the which thing is easy to be done: then with so great and importable charges, and with so longe tracte of tyme, to haue sought for the truthe in so many vniuersitis, in whiche are so many men of diuers opinions and wittes. <hi>AND</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the truthe, thus wel and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly knowen, his gracis cause hath ben by sufficiēt auctoritie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Englande, fully ended and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termined: wherin no man ought to doubte, the holy goste to be resident, as well as at Rome: as ryghte well maye appere by the epistole of Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane councell, writen vnto pope Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestine.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> yet for further contentacion of al men, so that none either lerned or vnlerned, shulde be with his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
<pb facs="tcp:176371:10"/> moste iuste cause and doinge her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in offended, consydering that a great parte of the worlde did beleue, as ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny yet dothe (other wyse then treuthe is) that the pope bi goddis lawe hath auctoritie aboue all other bishoppes, to here and determine causes within this realme of Englande: his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes attemperinge hym selfe to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmitie of the multitude, where he myghte lefully haue withstanded by his owne auctoritie, the popis vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped iurisdiction (wherby he wolde haue enforced our soueraygne to the breche of the lawe of god) and might right wel vnto hym haue sayde: we muste rather obeye god then men: he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note> hath frome all suche vsurpacion and other iniuries, wherwith the Poope wolde, if he had bene suffered, haue aggreued his highnesse: Frome all these (I sey) he hath appeled vnto the generall councell, and is herin (lyke a tru christened and a good catholike
<pb facs="tcp:176371:11"/> prince) very well contented to abyde suche determination, as the sayd coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celle nexte to be assembled in our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Iesu Christe, shall ordeyne.</p>
            <p>Nothinge herby doubtinge the iuste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his cause, so manifest to al the worlde: nor herby bringinge his said iuste cause, all redy well and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently determined, into controuersie and new sute: the whiche to do is not his gracis purpose.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> admitte that the pope had as great auctoritie, as he vsurpeth, and as the papistis wold fayne beare men in hande that he hath: yet coude he lette no man to appele from hym: for that were clerely ageynst the lawe of Nature, whiche is not contrarie to the lawe diuine. For then a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge harmed or wrongid by the pope, eyther in bodye, membres, or fame, shulde not in this case be holpen nor eased. And if it be leful for any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten man, what so euer he be, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pele
<pb facs="tcp:176371:11"/> to the councell generall, as it is in dede: then what iniurie dothe the pope to our souerayne, whiche dothe all that he can to driue hym from his appele? Yea what iniurie intendeth he to all men, whiche labourynge to make oure prince and kynge a presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, woll in tyme to come, suffre no man to appele frō his cursed courte?</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> though it were so, that the pope (admittynge hym to haue suche auctoritie) dyd to no man, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the wyll and worde of god: yet he can not chose, but is bounde to shewe the reason why he so dothe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Churche, whiche the general Councell, gethered in the holy goste, dothe represent: lyke as saincte Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Hierusalem, where the churche was, dyd mekely make answere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 11.</note> those that were of the circumcisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whiche disputed ageynste hym, sayenge: Why hast thou entred in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge, and eaten and dronke with
<pb facs="tcp:176371:12"/> those that be not circumcised? To this the holy apostoll dyd not onely, humblye and mekelye answerynge, shewe them the cause why he dyd it: but also he gaue a lesson to all them, that shulde folowe hym, humblie to do like wise: Be ye redy alwey, sayth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i.</hi> 3.</note> he, to answer &amp; satisfie euery mā that asketh you a reason of your feythe &amp; hope, with mekenes and reuerence.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>BY</hi> al these reasons it is to you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, that our souerayne hath now righte good cause to open vnto you, what maner of persone the byshoppe of Rome is, the whiche after manye monitions, refuseth at length to here the churche, that is to wytte the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall councell, but woll hym selfe be iudge at his owne pleasure: he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cethe not for the doctrine of Christe, nor for the example of Peter, nor his teachinge, but sayth he woll be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and accordynge to his lawes, the whiche be none other but his owne
<pb facs="tcp:176371:12"/> wyl, he wol haue vs do.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>MORE</hi> ouer, if any papiste wyll come yet forthe and tell you, that the pope may do what he wyl, and maye bynde and leuse what he lysteth here on erthe, bicause Christe sayde to Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th.</hi> 6.</note> I wol gyue to the, the keys of the kyngedome of heuen: lette hym not therwith blynde and deceyue you.</p>
            <p>For saincte Augustine, spekynge of these keys in his fyrste boke <hi>De doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na christiana,</hi> sayth thus: Those keyes he gaue to his churche, that what so euer the churche wolde leuse in erthe, shulde be lowsed in heuen: and what so euer the churche shulde bynde in erthe, shulde be bounde in heuen.</p>
            <p>Nowe it is wel proued to you before, that the pope is nother the churche, nor the heed therof, but a membre (if he be a christen man) and the childe of our mother the holy churche.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> ferther if any wyll yet telle you, that at the leeste wyse the Pope
<pb facs="tcp:176371:13"/> hath the keye of diuine knoweledge, wherof Christe speketh Luce. xi. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he so haue or no, ye shal perceyue it thus: The glose seythe, that this keye is the humilitie of Christe, the whiche who so hath, hath the gaate open to the vnderstandinge of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Nowe take heede and se whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope haue this humilytie: Christe the very sonne of god, dydde <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</hi> 2.</note> humble hym selfe euyn to the veray dethe, yea to the shamefull dethe of the crosse: The pope (ye se very well) woll be exalted aboue all other, in so moche that kynges, princis, dukes, and lordes muste kneele to hym and kysse his feete, and do to hym all the honoure and worshyppe, that can be deuised in this worlde. Wherfore it appereth playnely, that he hath not this keye of knoweledge, whiche is Christis humilitie.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ALSO</hi> this keye of knoweledge may be taken and called the feythe,
<pb facs="tcp:176371:13"/> accordynge as Esaye, the prophette <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esaie.</hi> 7.</note> saythe: Except ye woll beleue, ye can not vnderstande. Nowe marke wel whether the Pope haue this keye of feythe or no. Christe saythe, that he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.</note> that hath as moche feythe as a lytell mustarde sede, shall be able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande mountaynes to remoue from one place to an other: and ther shuld be nothynge impossible vnto hym. And agayne Christe sayth: All thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 19.</note> are possible to him that beleueth. And agayne yet he saythe in an other place: He that beleueth in me, shall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 14.</note> do the warkes that I do, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then those. This is to vnderstād, that if the pope were ioynid to Christ in his feythe, as the apostols were, he shulde be able to do lyke as the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postols dyd, that is to wytte, by his preachynge of the gospell truely, he shulde conuerte and turne nations of mysbeleuynge people, to the feythe of Iesu Christe. Whiche thynge all
<pb facs="tcp:176371:14"/> the worlde seeth playnly he doth not: but by his pryde, his tyrannye, and mooste greuous exactions he hathe and dothe (I feare me) compell great multitudes of people and hole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys &amp; nations, to forsake the feithe of Christe. Wherfore seinge he hath nother the keys of heuen, nor the key of diuine knoweledge, nor the key of feythe: I can perceyue none other, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.</note> but that he is the vnsauery salt, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of our sauiour Christe speketh in the gospell, whiche is no better worthe, but to be throwen out of the doores, and to be trodde vnder mens feete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> nowe to come to a conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this lytell treatise: Where as it hath ben spokē of many and diuers, that it was a mery world before men spake of any suche mattiers, that is to witte, to haue any reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge theim of the clergie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that men beganne to sette lyght the pope, and to call hym the bishop
<pb facs="tcp:176371:14"/> of Rome: that is as wyse a sayenge and opinion, as this is of them that sey, sens the crienge downe of Galy halfpens, the lernynge of Duns ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer prosperedde, And also sens Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdyn steple was builded, Sandwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hauen hath euer more decayed. But I praye you beholde, howe the fauourers of blynde abusion wolde fayne blowe abrode smokie and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie reasons to darke &amp; dymme mens eies with all. They sey it was merie before suche mattiers were moued, but they tell not what tyme it was, with whome, nor wherin it was me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And if they meane, that the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and commons of this realme of Englande hadde more riches, and greatter plentie of foode and vitaile, and lyued in moche more welthe, and more at theyr hartis ease in lauful li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: then lette them consider, that this was before the pope and his cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie were growen so great, so stronge
<pb facs="tcp:176371:15"/> and myghty, and to so huge possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and riches, as they welde at this daye: for before that tyme they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the gospelle trewlye, they were meke and lowly spirited, and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encye was to them abundaunce, they were charitable, they were milde and mercifull, and gaue good example, and men gladly folowed them, then reigned loue &amp; liberalitie, then there was peace and vnitie, that causedde great plentie in euery place: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were ones endowed with pos<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sessions, and theyr myndes inordiat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drowned in them, and that Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnes beganne to crepe in amonge them, after that (I saye) folowed all mischiefe and miserie, all wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and penurie: The pope, he pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a pace for his parte: yea whome wolde it not make right soroweful &amp; heuy in harte to remembre, what ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches this cursed caytiffe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pope hath polled out of this realme by the space
<pb facs="tcp:176371:15"/> of these thre hundred yeres, ye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in these. xl. yeres, or within these. xx. yeres? What pilleth he yerely? what myscheuous meanes doth he inuent and seke out, to robbe and spoyle vs of our welthe? What lawes hath he deuysed, what legations, what and howe many dyuerse courtes? What dispensations, what pencions out of abbeys exempt, what peter pens out of parishes, what reseruaciōs, what constitutions, what citations, what suspencions, what pardones, what kynde of cursynges, &amp; blessynges &amp; absolucions? what wyles, what gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, what fraudes, what diuilishe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes and snares, are daylie couert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly couched to catche coyne frome the peple? Oh good lorde, how the pope and his minysters dayly deuyse and practise to polle and pylle the people of this realme of theyr money? And yet I speke nothinge of the great vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quietnes and vexacion that many se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:176371:16"/> soules haue, ouer and besides the losse of theyr goodes. He the moste vnhappy patrone and his, be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cause of all our miserie, of all our scarsitie, and of all our vexacion and trowble. Who be the occasion and styrrers vppe of warre and stryffe in Christendome, but the pope and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistis? Looke who so lysteth, and he shall surely fynde, that the pope and his, to saue and kepe vppe styll theyr pompose and worldly state, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wey ben the inuenters of myschieffe and destruction of people, by theyr vngodlye instigations of pryncis to warre. Yea if the trouthe shulde be shewed of the great ruyne that hath rysen by them and theyr meanes, in Christendome, it wolde abhorre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, were he neuer so partiall on the popis syde, eyther to rede or here it. But I woll lette that passe, I am right sory, that we shulde haue cause to shewe you so moche of hym as I
<pb facs="tcp:176371:16"/> haue done, saue alonely I wolde all suche as be blynded, or be ignorant, shulde perceyue: that our moste gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious soueraygne lorde the kynge, is moste specially mouedde to do as he dothe, of his princely pitie and zele, that his highnes beareth to his true and louynge subiectes. Surely I say, this his tyrannie and pyllage in maner constraynethe the kynge his grace, to delyuer this his realme frō the captiuitie &amp; bondage of the pope: and kepe within the sayd realme (for the welthe and safegard of the same) the great and huge somes of money, that were wont to runne to Rome.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AND</hi> if it be not sufficient inough to persuade some of you, to se and so clerely to beholde, howe clene contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie to the lawe of god the pope deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hym selfe, the which he is boūde in all that euer he may do, to folowe: then at the leeste wyse lette the great miserie and pore state, that this most
<pb facs="tcp:176371:17"/> noble, and sometyme the moste flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shynge realme of Christendome, is broughte into by the pollynge of the pope, moue and sturre you to stande styffely with our moste benigne and louynge souerayne lorde and prince, that is fully bente and gothe aboute to ridde his realme of this thraldom, and to restore and brynge it agayne out of pouertie to plentie, and frome rauyne to riches, and from trowble and greuous vexacion to quietnesse and reste, and so finally to al the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer welthy state. Whervnto as good and trewe subiectes, with all youre hartis ye are also boūde by the lawes of god, his quarel beinge thus iuste, and he intendynge so greate a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to all the realme. Accordyng as the holy apostol Paule sayth: Let <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.</note> euery soule be subiecte to the high po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wers: for the powers that be, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of god. So that he that resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth the high power, resisteth the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
<pb facs="tcp:176371:17"/> of god. And they that resiste, seke theyr owne damnacion. Loke howe straytely the apostoll byndethe vs to the obedience of our prince: for in the same chapitre he nameth none other powers, but onely of princis.</p>
            <p>And the holy apostol Peter likewise <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri,</hi> 2.</note> dothe commande vs to demeane our<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfes lyke lowely and obedient sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, whether it be to the kyng hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe, as to the moste chiefe and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of all, orels to the dukes and go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernours, that are sent by hym. And consequently he saythe: Honour the kynge. Nowe seinge that we be commanded by the holy scripture, to loue, to obey, and honour our prince, not only outwardly in bodies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so inwardly in our hartes, withoute any dissimulacion or feynynge, and that bicause he is the minister of god, and dothe represent and occupie the place of god here in erthe: howe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more then are we bounde to loue,
<pb facs="tcp:176371:18"/> to obeye, to honoure, and ayde oure moste gratious prince, with all oure very hartis, whiche specially for our sakes taketh so great peyne, and that so diligentely dothe seke the meanes howe to ridde vs out of bondage, out of miserie, out of nede and vexacion, that we be broughte into by the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnes of the brybynge byshoppe of Rome (the whyche by that name of Pope polleth and pylfereth awey the riches of this realme) and that so mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che myndeth to restore vs to all oure olde welthynes and libertie ageyne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THVS</hi> ye se playnly proued to you by reason and auctorite of holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that we do none other wyse in oure tyme nowe, then oure wise and well lerned fore fathers dyd, though the tyme then wolde not suffre them to bringe to passe their well intended purpose. And it is shewed, that the olde holy doctours of Christis chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che afferme, that nother custome, nor
<pb facs="tcp:176371:18"/> vsage shulde be regarded, when the truthe ones appereth, but the truthe shulde be enbraced and folowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> also it is wel proued that our prince &amp; souerayne dothe it not nowe for or of any yuell wyl or displeasure: for they that eyther so thynke or sey, do thynke and sey vntrewly, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydes that, in theyr so doinge, they greatly offende god. for it is writen: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 22. <hi>Eccl</hi> 10.</note> Thou shalte not speke yuell by the prince of the people. And agayne it is writen: In thy thought thou shul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest not detracte the kinge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> it is like wyse manifestly pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, that thoughe the pope hadde as great auctoritie, as he vsurpeth and taketh on hym to haue: yet coulde he let no man to appele from hym.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> it is lyke wyse proued, that the pope is neyther the catholyke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly churche of Christe, nor yet the heed of the same, but if he be a Christen man, he is the childe of our mother
<pb facs="tcp:176371:19"/> the holy churche, and brother to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry christen man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> finally it is like wise shewed, that the miserie, nede, pouertie, and scacitie, that we be in, cometh all to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether by the pope and his meanes. Frome whome and whose captiuite, Christe delyuer vs, that boughte vs on a tree. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176371:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>